which yl
go package module Library should you
use uh I got this question yesterday
somebody said why are you using and I
quote the out ofate yaml V3 instead of
using the
kubernetes yaml
parser so this video hopefully it will
be short but I'm going to answer the
question the reason I'm going to you I
use the AML V3 is because it's the most
modern it's the most well established
and it has the least amount of drama and
that last one is kind of an interesting
one uh because the drama actually exists
between the kubernetes project and the
yaml
project so let's go into that so here I
have the different code bases so right
off the bat you'll see uh the gi.com
goyl which by the way this is not the
name of the package the package name is
go
pg. yl. V3 which uses the original
method
of um distinguishing between different
versions of of packages and modules and
go before modules were a thing so that's
why it's there and but the but the
definitive location for the source is go
yaml yaml that's what we're looking at
here uh when you look at the tag here
um whoops let's go in here now you'll
see okay so this is using you see how
the branch is V3 this is using the
branching method of Distinction that is
recognized by go uh go modules are very
hard to understand for a lot of
beginners uh and Veterans alike but this
gives us kind of a place to look uh for
for that
um so what are we looking at we're
looking at the source code for yaml V3
uh the yaml package enables go programs
to comfortably encode and decode yaml
values uh it was originally developed by
canonical and then picked up uh and for
that
reason you will see a lot of weirdness
in here um and that is for a different
video I've done my own as rwx Rob yaml
library to deal with other stuff here
I'll make a separate video on that make
sure you watch that video but the while
I was working on that I was asked why I
wasn't using the other one so in in
window 3 over here on kubernetes we have
the source code for github.com
kubernetes uh- sigs SL thanks for the
follow SL
yaml and the first thing you might
notice just coming into this thing is
that you have a go yl. V3 and a go yl.
V2 like well what is up with that and if
you open up the read me you'll see
what's
up um the marshalling and marshalling
support for go here's the build status
blah blah blah this is a wrapper this is
very important
information this kubernetes project
which is called kubernetes sigs this is
a sub project special interest group for
kubernetes that focuses on this
particular thing parsing yaml reliably
for kubernetes this says and as it says
in introduction this is a wrapper
around go Dash yaml yaml designed to
enable a quote better way of handling
yaml when marshalling to and from
structs that better way that that
statement about it being a better way is
the reason that there is drama between
the kubernetes project and the yl
project and we'll get to that so in
short this Library first converts yaml
to Json using go yaml and then uses Json
Marshall and on Marshall to convert it
okay so this there's a lot of problems
with this
because this introduction this this is
extremely confusing my friends and in
fact it took me quite a while to undo it
when I went to the website and let's do
that now when I went to the website
where are you GitHub GitHub GitHub
GitHub all right let's do this uh
github.com
what is it sigs
something kubernetes Sig okay kubernetes
Sig there it is when I when you first go
out to the website for this project
you'll immediately notice that it is
forked from God's yaml which is by the
way a really awesome package but it is
not a base yaml
parser this thing has a dependency
itself on the underlying yaml V3 and and
this is kind of hard for beginners to
figure out how to navigate it if I were
to draw a map which I'm not but if I
were I tell you what Let's do let's do
it let's air dry well air drw okay so so
over here you have the kuet project
right and over here you have well sort
of way up here you have the yaml V3
project which is an extension of the
yaml V2 project which originally came
from canonical okay and then after that
you have the gods project the one the
one that you just saw that it was forked
from and this is extremely misleading if
you're looking at the kubernetes project
you're like oh this project is a fork of
God's SL yaml that is actually true it's
also consistent with the introduction
which is extremely hard to understand
because let's read it again this is
wrong okay um this introduction here it
is this is okay I I take it back I take
it back here it is right here kubernetes
s jaml is a permanent Fork
of the Gods yl project which is an
encapsulation around this project so
what is unclear in fact this just
confused me while making this video even
now is like what the hell is this thing
what the hell am I looking at kubernetes
Sig yaml should I use it number one is
the first question but before I even ask
that answer that question I have to know
what the hell it is well I'll tell you
what it's not kubernetes 6- yaml is not
an original project as it says right
there kubernetes Sig yaml is a permanent
Fork that by the way is not very
wellmaintained it has not been kept up
to date I happen to know and it is a
fork of a project that was designed you
can go look at it to
wrap the actual yaml project this is so
important right here all right so it is
wrapping the official yaml parser which
is yaml V3 the one that I have been
using and then I have been modifying not
modifying but you know adding helper
support so so let me just I have to come
back to this because the statement was
rather in my face the other day and they
said and I again I quote why are you
using an outdated yaml module
for your
helper and as you can see now I am not I
am using the standard yaml package and
module from which these others have
diverted or that they have wrapped in
fact to use the exact language of the
package this is a wrapper around yaml V3
designed to enable a better way of
handling yaml when Mar to and from strs
most importantly allowing the use of the
Json tags so you don't have to have yaml
and Json tags and that is kind of
convenient but it is a wrapper it is an
extension of what I agree that they
would probably agree is the standard
which is go- yaml yaml in other words go
PKG here's how you do the import uh so
here the one from canonical okay which
is by the way and not even original it's
an extension uh it's a it's an Implement
a go implementation of a sea library
that was
generated that is a lot of history but
but I think the important part to take
away from this here we are looking at
the at the kubernetes one again is that
the standard that is used for
kubernetes is a fork of a wrapper for
the actual yaml module this standard
module
so I want to just I'm going to say it
again I can't get tired of saying this
the kubernetes project has decided to
use a module that is two
dependencies away from the standard and
on top of that add a third problem
Divergence by not maintaining its vendor
copy of it and by the way since we're on
the topic of vendors do you notice
something interesting here again this is
the kubernetes version
let's let's look at some other problems
with it the first look at this
1.12
right 1.12 and if you were looking at
this you'd be like does this even use go
yaml you're like well not according to
the requirement here you know why
because they vendored it incorrectly uh
that's not fair they vendored it in a
way that you would do in 1.12
they did not have a vendor directory
right in 2024 if you are not doing go
mod vendor to vendor your stuff you're
doing it
wrong G mod vendor creates what is now
become a
standard the standard being Thou shalt
put all your vendor stuff in the vendor
directory all the go tooling notices
this and it's now no longer it's no
longer thing so so you would have no way
to know that go yaml V3 and V2 are
actually being vendored vendoring being
the inclusion of something um and there
they are they are included they are
vendored um and you know they they are
not even doing it in a standard way so
you know if there if there's one thing
you can conclude here the kubernetes
project is way way behind and they have
no intention of keeping up and that
leads into the drama and I don't know
all the
details I honestly can't even remember
where I read it so I'm just telling you
that straight up
but as I remember and this was a long
time ago as I remember the kubernetes
project had there was a breaking change
made by the yaml
team uh in a
nonbreaking version of yaml I think it
was
V2 and was and they changed the number
of spaces in the indentation I believe
that was it and it broke it actually
broke uh the kubernetes project and they
got mad and you can probably find the
issue out there and they went ahead and
they re they re redid it they brought it
uh they actually reverted the change
it's very rare that they did that and
they I don't know what they did with the
version numbers or something like that
but as far as I know and again don't
quote me on this I believe that was the
source of the drama
where that caused things like this to be
written in the read me of the kubernetes
yaml
project um the decision to permanently
Fork this other
project which you know it's kind of
interesting it didn't just permanently
Fork this project it also permanently
forked go yaml V3 and go yaml
V2 so think about that for a second that
that you don't even know what so you
would never know that you would have to
really really dig to understand what is
actually going on in this kubernetes
project with regard to yaml because
you're like down here I say what's up
with this go yaml thing you know you
says this a permanent Fork of this but
that means it must be also a permanent
Fork of this right and you would there
is no mention of that but by finding it
by looking at it over here and then
looking at the build scripts you can
figure out that that's what they're
doing they are building from a not this
isn't in a subm module either this isn't
a get subm module this is just a random
directory that's been copied
that contains all of the source at some
random point in time which shall not be
known we do not know what time when
which version this is we have no
idea there we go this package is a fork
of the goyama lmer is ATT tenden to for
consumption by kubernetes in this work
we plan to support only critical changes
required for kubernetes such as small
bug fixes and regressions large larger
general purpose spee request should be
made Upstream to the Goyo project we
will reject any such changes for this SP
unless we are pulling them from Upstream
all right now let's come back to the
question I'm not I'm sorry the statement
that was made at me while I was doing my
thing the statement was why would you
use the out ofd non-net version when
there's a much more recent version does
this look recent to
you the only time anybody would even
make that statement would be if they had
not read the readme from this package so
yeah I'm a little bit ranty there
because right there it tells you the
very reason I would never look at this
thing ever and neither should you this
package this random copied code from the
project that had we don't even know what
version it is is based on the fork 3.0.1
which I guarantee you is no longer
accurate and they have only been making
individual bug PES and regressions which
you cannot know know without looking it
up in the commit history of this project
that means that they have decided to
fork for whatever reason because they do
not want to deal with the changes of the
other project and that is their
prerogative but why on Earth would I
ever build a dependency on a project
that has decided willfully to Fork the
standard project for yaml and also say
we have no intention of ever updating
except for the changes we want why would
I ever want to use that in any project
that I build that ever uses yaml unless
I agreed with the kubernetes team that
the yaml team doesn't know what they're
doing because that's the implied
statement here the implied statement is
we don't like the yaml project so we're
going to Fork it and go we're going to
you know Fork
you we're gonna go do our own thing so
the answer to why I am using the
standard yaml project is because I want
my code to be standard I want it to have
Upstream changes to the official yaml V3
project which is overwhelmingly used as
a dependency in every project on the
planet besides kubernetes and I'm going
to take this moment to say what I have
said many times kubernetes code is
it is the worst code I have ever seen
for any major project in go
sorry do not look at
kubernetes as a way to write go it is
one of the worst projects ever you want
a lot of good projects ask me I'll tell
you there's kind there's uh Argo CD is a
phenomenal project there is uh go
releaser there there are so many awesome
awesome go projects to learn how to
write go code well the kubernetes
codebase is not it in fact run screaming
from the kubernetes code base it is
horrible it's one of the most horrible
go code bases I've ever seen in my
entire life so for the go project for
the for the kubernetes project to say oh
we know better than the yaml
project no I don't trust them at all
they've already destroy their reputation
just by the code they released it's
absolute and and I can't believe
the whole world is dependent on it
honest of God I really can't that's
probably a good place for me to
stop talk to you later